<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclimation, by the which is prohibited in the research of the passengers ships betweene France and England, not to vse any disorder in words nor deedes, neither to vse any bad or slaunderous speeches of the Kings Maiestie of Great Britaine, &amp;c. nor his subiects in any manner whatsoeuer translated out of Dutch.</title>
            <title>Placcaet daer by verboden wort int recherceren vande passagiers schepen. English</title>
            <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18454.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4398</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24347206</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24347206</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08090)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1822:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclimation, by the which is prohibited in the research of the passengers ships betweene France and England, not to vse any disorder in words nor deedes, neither to vse any bad or slaunderous speeches of the Kings Maiestie of Great Britaine, &amp;c. nor his subiects in any manner whatsoeuer translated out of Dutch.</title>
                  <title>Placcaet daer by verboden wort int recherceren vande passagiers schepen. English</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 3 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Purfoot, for William Fearbrand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1605]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Placcaet daer by verboden wort int recherceren vande passagiers schepen ..., 1605.--Cf. Petit 814.</note>
                  <note>"Thus done and concluded by the sayd lords, the Generall Estates being assembled in S'Grauenhaghen, the nineteenth of July anno. 1605."--P. [3]</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ (first leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History, Naval.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  1556-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27548:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:27548:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
            <p>A PROCLIMATION, BY THE WHICH IS prohibited in the reſearch of the <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers Ships betweene France and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, not to vſe any diſorder in words nor</hi> deedes, neither to vſe any bad or ſlaunderous ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Kings Maieſtie of Great <hi>Britaine, &amp;c. nor his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in any manner whatſoeuer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Dutch.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Thomas Purfoot, for William Fearbrand.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:27548:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:27548:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He generall Eſtates of the vnited Low-countreys. To all thoſe that ſhall ſee theſe preſents or heare them to be read, ſend greeting and let to wete, or make knowne. Whereas we are informed, that in the reſearch of Paſſengers ſhips between France &amp; England by the Ships of Warre, which are in ſeruice of theſe Countreys, to the end to know whether in the ſame there be any Souldiors going towardes the Enemie, or other perſons actually of the ſeruice of the Enemie, many abuſes &amp; wrongs are offered by the Ships Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and others which do abord the ſaid Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers Ships, as beating, thruſting, wronging, and ryfling of the Paſſengers contrarie to our order, good intention, inſtruction and all reaſon. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that the Ships Company through ignorance, and otherwiſe in the meane time vpon the Ships, but eſpectally in the ſayd reſearch, doe ſpeake hardly of the Kings Maieſtie of Great Britaine &amp;c. From whom the vnited Prouinces, and the Inhabitants of the ſame, many yeeres haue enioyed, and as yet doe enioy many Royall fauors and pleaſures; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence that his Maieſtie hath made Peace with the King of Spaine: notwithſtanding his Maieſtie by reaſon thereof, hath not changed, alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nor diminiſhed his affections towards theſe Countteys in the leaſt point, wherein they doe not onely wronge his Maieſtie, but alſo vs the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the vnited Prouinces in generall. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as euerie one is holden and bound to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to requite his Maieſties good affection &amp; great fauors with due thanks, and the ſame to win and
<pb facs="tcp:27548:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->conſerue for theſe Countreys, and that ſuch miſrules and vnlawful reſearch, as alſo the ſaid bad ſpeeches and abuſes might happen to breede a diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between his Maieſtie and his Subiects with the Inhabitants of the vnited Prouinces, to the preiudice of the welfare of theſe Countreys, wherein it is needfull by times by all meanes to foreſee. Therefore haue we expreſly forbidden and prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, doe forbid and prohibite by theſe preſents all and ſingul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of what condition or qualitie they be, and namely the Commanders ſhippe, Captaines, ſhippe Officers, and Mariners of the ſhips of war of our Fleete, which doe lye in waight in the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Seas and vpon the coaſts of Flaunders, and all others which ſhall be commaunded for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearch of the ſayd Paſſengers ſhips between Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Fraunce, not to vſe any diſorder or vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes by words or deeds, but to doe the ſame with all diſcretion without beating, thruſting, wronging, or ryfling any one. And further we doe forbid all the Inhabitants of the vnited Prouinces and others frequenting the ſame: as alſo al thoſe as are in our ſeruice by water or by land, not to vſe any bad or iniurious ſpeeches of the Kings moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie of Great Britaine, &amp;c. nor of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in any manner of wiſe, nor to ſlaunder nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute them with any calumnious ſpeeches, vnder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretence whatſoeuer, vpon paine to be puniſhed, (as diſturbers of the Common welfare) in bodie and goods, without contradiction or delay. Prouided alwayes, that we doe not herewith exempt thoſe of what Nation or condition ſoeuer they be, which ſhalbe found by the ſayd reſearch in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Paſſengers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27548:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->Ships going to the ſeruice of the King of Spaine, or of the Arch-Dukes, nor thoſe which ſhalbe found to be in their ſeruice, but our expreſſe intention and commiſſion is, that ſuch ſhalbe dealt withall and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed according to the order to that effect giuen in the Fleete. And to the end no man doe pretend to be ignorant of theſe preſents, we doe ordaine and giue commiſſion to our welbeloued the Eſtates, Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, and committed counſell of the ſeuerall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces of <hi>Gelderland,</hi> and Countie of <hi>Sutfen, Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſtfreeſland, Sealand</hi> and <hi>Wretcht, Freeſland, Oueriſſell,</hi> the Towne of <hi>Greenighen,</hi> and places adioyning, and all others Iuſtices, Officers, and Miniſters being thereunto required, to make knowne, proclayme and publiſh this our order in all places, where it is vſuall to publiſh &amp; proclayme, charging alſo the Gouernors, Preſidents, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall Counſell: likewiſe the Colledges of the Admiraltie, the Fiſcalladuocats, and alſo the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Atturneys, and all other Officers, Iudges, and Iuſtices of the ſayd Countreys, and likewiſe the Admiral, Vice-Admirals, Chiefetaines, Collonels, Commaunders, Captaines, and Officers to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh, and cauſe to be accompliſhed this our order, and to proceed, &amp; cauſe to be proceeded againſt theſe which ſhall doe any thing to the contrarie, without any fauour, grace, diſſembling, or forbearance, for ſuch is our expreſſe meaning.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Thus done and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the ſayd Lords<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the generall Eſtates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſembled in <hi>S'Grauenhaghen,</hi> 
                  <date>the Nineteenth of Iuly <hi>Anno. 1605.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>And was ſubſcribed in <hi>Eluckema VI.</hi>
               </signed>
               <signed>Vnder is written by order of the ſayd Lords the generall Eſtates ſubſcribed. <hi>G. Aerſſen.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
